it's easy to have people think that
taking a calcium supplement will either
preserve bone health or stop it from
declining in the first place
unfortunately it doesn't really pan out
like that the vast majority of the time
as long as you're kind of hitting medium
numbers something like 800 to 1,000
milligrams of caffeine or calcium rather
per day you tend to be fine adding a
calcium supplement on on top of that
doesn't seem to have much of an impact
on overall bone health um now this is
another case where it's sort of like if
you're in the low end of the spectrum so
say you're in a position of low food
quality or you can't eat it or a kid
won't eat it or something like that then
going from low to normal there might be
a place but going from normal to high in
terms of calcium intake doesn't seem to
make much of an impact you're probably
just going to excrete most of that back
out now in terms of like getting 800 to
1,000 Mig of of calcium per day it's not
particularly hard
biggest places you're going to get them
from most common ones are things like
yogurt cheese dairy products I think the
average glass of milk has like 300
milligrams so you know in in passing
with most people if you're eating
somewhat amounts of reasonable real food
you're you're probably going to get
somewhat close to that it's just a
threshold issue right so if you're
getting it in food you're okay you don't
need it if you're not getting it then
this is when supplements would turn to
be the case so I would differentiate the
impact of calcium supplements based upon
kids and adults most part adults don't
see much of an impact there um the data
are very mixed to not impressive kids if
it's low take it if not you should be
fine the next thing on our list is
actually surprising enough protein
there's a really cool paper that came
out uh quite uh it's actually been a few
years now I think
2019 um dietary protein and bone health
across the life course it's an updated
systematic review and met analysis over
40 years this one actually catches
people off guard a lot they do not
realize the protein intake has on bone
health that doesn't seem to be a
connection there they don't understand
why lots of different things going be
happening here but it may and I
emphasize May um enhance bone health by
improving calcium absorption um thing
called igf1 uh by increasing lean bone
mass or lean body mass itself and so
kind of these like secondary actions uh
tend to be the the most prominent
likelihood of why protein intake uh
helps with bone health um also accounts
for some of the neighbor like 2 to 4% of
the overall variance in bone mineral
density so it's an impactful thing but
it is not nearly as impactful as all the
other stuff we've been talking about
thus far fish oil is another supplement
that'll come up really routinely it's
honestly like a pretty similar story
here there's a lot of really good
research in animals some stuff in human
admittedly it's more mixed some of them
been really impressive other ones have
been saying ah okay there's not much
here it's likely very very dose and
condition dependent and I and I think
this theme will run through of just
about everything in this category so you
know what I mean when I say that if
they're really bad the supplement helps
if they're okay in this area the
supplement probably doesn't have as much
of an in fact but like protein there's
so many documented benefits of fish oil
it's just it's just almost a no risk
potential reward scenario so why not now
collagen is another one remember the
bulk of your bone is made of collagen uh
been a lot of research well more recent
research on this stuff um looking at
things that are called specific collagen
peptides now we can perhaps later you
can Google what that means but there
have been randomized control trials in
women post-menopausal women um that have
looked at these things and in general it
seems to be pretty positive right bone
Minal density in the spine specifically
and for moral neck uh increased
significantly with collagen intake and I
think this I'm pretty sure this was
actually done at five grams of collagen
per day that's a really low amount if
you were to get collagen um I know
specifically the one that momentus makes
momentus of course is a sponsor of this
show and I've long been involved with
that company personally I think that
their serving size is 20 grams and so
five grams is a very very modest amount
the fact that they saw benefits in two
very important sites in boneal density
with five grams uh per day of collagen
is really really impactful uh and I and
I think Monumental I haven't seen a ton
of follow-up studies on this I'm not
exactly sure why but you could dive into
the details uh of some of this research
and again I think you're going to be
more impressed this is another one that
like really surprises people they don't
realize these data are out there and the
the the magnitude of impact is really
impressive you're talking about like
four to 7% increases in bone Minal
density um over a 12- month span right
so again they're doubling the length
here so we see more Improvement but as
we've talking about um that that's quite
a bit so something I think certainly is
worth paying attention
to and considering again not a lot of
downside potentially You could argue
that the cost is a little bit high but
that's really it and has a a reasonable
chance to create some benefits here if
you enjoyed this clip you can watch the
full episode by clicking here
[Music]